Okay, so we're going to look at some common issues that we need to take into consideration.
Data transferred into ZOS from any non-ZOS platform probably requires ASCII to epsidic
translation. Most workstation and UNIX systems store their data in ASCII format. Also, the
terminals on those systems use the ASCII format for display characters. The translation is
easy to do if the file is all text data. The transfer tool that you use has the capability
to specify conversion. For example, a PAX command explodes, translates, and decompresses
a file archived on a UNIX system. NFS and FTP do this translation automatically unless
the data is defined as binary. You can also customize the translation tables that these
tools use. If your data is part numeric and part text, you might have to do some translation
manually on a field-by-field basis. Some sorting functions might give different results
on an epsidic system from an ASCII system, and this difference might require some application
changes. COS UNIX is epsidic. Most other UNIX platforms are ASCII. ASCII programs with
nasty dirty programming like that shown here cannot be easily ported. Now, one solution
is programs can be compiled as ASCII programs. Programs are marked in USS if they are epsidic
or ASCII. Another problem that occurs when porting programs is IOTA files, which was
originally ASCII. Solutions here include keeping the file as ASCII, marking the file as ASCII,
and let auto-conversion be done in the USS logical file system, or tagging the file
as a text file with coded character set ID, or CCSID, of 819. If you're not using
enhanced ASCII and auto-conversion, then currently there are few facilities available on ZOS
to display and change ASCII or Unicode data. You can't use ISPF or OEdit. The increasing
use of Java on ZOS and the use of ASCII encoded XML documents means there is more
and more ASCII data being stored on ZOS. Unfortunately, it's generally necessary for
ZOS users to download ASCII data to a workstation supporting the ASCII character set in order
to view or change this data. Since the ISPF editor is the most popular and well-known
editor on ZOS, the benefit of being able to display and change ASCII data on ZOS is
best delivered by adding this support to the ISPF editor. With ZOS, use the source
ASCII and LF commands to edit ASCII data stored in ZOS datasets. For Unix files, you have
to use ISPF 3.17, EA, edit an ASCII file, or VA, view an ASCII file. We're showing
an example of using the edit source ASCII and LF commands to display ASCII data. To
activate the ASCII editing facility for a file, the user will first start editing the
file as they would for a normal EBCDIC file. When the editor primary line command source
ASCII is entered, the editor will treat the source data as though it is ASCII data
and it will convert it from ASCII to the CCSID of the terminal for display purposes,
although the data will remain unchanged within the file itself. When the user add the terminal
inputs or modifies data at the terminal, the editor will translate the data entered from
the CCSID of the terminal to ASCII prior to storing the data in the file. The edit
reset primary command has been modified to support the source keyword, which will cause
the editor to revert back to a normal mode where the data is not translated from and
to ASCII when displaying and receiving input from the terminal.
In the final video in this module, we're going to revisit everybody's favourite topic,
code pages.